Today on the podcast, I sat down with Mark Ko, the founder and CIO of Intrinsic Edge
Capital Management, a long short hedge fund based in Chicago.
We originally had Mark on the podcast four years ago when he launched his Digital Infrastructure
Fund, a vehicle that makes investments in public equities in the blockchain industry.
And a lot has definitely changed over those last four years with many more public names
and the complete evolution of the Bitcoin mining industry with the emergence of LLMs.
I think you'll enjoy this conversation.
So without further ado, here's Mark Ko.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, 85 billion dollars.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin, Bitcoin.
Mark, I can't believe it's been four years since the last time you were on this podcast.
Thankfully, we talk a lot in the interim, but four years, we're doing this every Olympics,
it sounds like.
It's uncanny, man.
I can't believe it.
Just thinking back to what the world looked like back then versus now, obviously we're
going to have a ton to talk about on the podcast.
Maybe a good place to start for folks that didn't listen to the first time you were on
the podcast.
Let's just start with maybe a little bit of background on you and what is Intrinsic Edge?
Yeah, sure, Matt.
I was raised in Chicago, background as in finance and as a CPA.
In my early 20s, I developed a passion for investing, all sorts of investing.
And for me, it's a hobby.
In my 30s, I launched Intrinsic Edge Capital Management, which was in the 1990s.
It dates me. And Intrinsic Edge Capital Management is in the public markets and it's
in equities. We run a long, short domestic equity strategy.
We're generalists and been doing it a long time.
We have several funds and we built the firm and the team.
We've got about 20 employees, hundreds of investors and still having a lot of fun
doing it. And we cover different industries.
And going back four years ago, we launched this digital infrastructure
strategy and look forward to talking about it today.
Well, I definitely want to talk about the digital infrastructure strategy, and I guess I
should disclose that I'm an investor, a happy investor in that fund.
Maybe just dialing back the clock on that, what was the impetus to even start the
digital infrastructure fund and maybe talk a little bit about what it's been like over
the past couple of years?
There was a lot of enthusiasm.
This goes back like five years ago where Bitcoin made its earlier run and people
were trying to understand what was going on and how to invest.
And I had some curiosity.
I invested in Castle Island and some other strategies.
But this wasn't a discipline that I had a great understanding for.
And when clients would ask me, you know, what do I think and how do I invest?
I didn't have a great answer for them as I was kind of developing my understanding.
But there was enough interest that I started looking into the public markets and
equities that had touch store were predominantly exposed to blockchain and
crypto businesses.
That is a discipline I really understand as a generalist.
We think about revenues and margins and earnings and putting evaluation on it.
And for every industry that's an operating business is pretty much the same.
So I had a lot of inquiries.
We were doing work in the public markets and it was really exciting.
And we launched that fund in June of 2021.
And you asked a kind of about the journey, as we all know, it's been a cyclical
market. Historically, it wasn't a great time to start the fund because certainly
thereafter that meltdown had started and Bitcoin, which was trading in the 30s,
traded down to the mid teens.
And the public equities are correlated to the underlying crypto.
And the equities are measured by BLOK, which is a ETF.
They were down like 80 percent from peak to trough from 21 to 22.
It wasn't a very fun time considering we were a long bias fund.
We had a monstera down and I was really wondering why we ever got into this.
But that was the impetus.
And then things in the ecosystem bottom.
And we came off of that trough with results that I'm proud of the last few
years and going strong.
That's an understatement, to say the least, on the results side.
So maybe a good place to also just dive in here would be the categories of
businesses that are even interesting or addressable for you.
I'd imagine that a lot of these things looked like just Bitcoin mining companies
in the early days. And curious what that landscape looks like now in terms of the
categories of businesses that you would even evaluate an investment in.
It really is interesting.
And it's really morphed into there's been a convergence of industries
between traditional businesses and blockchain infrastructure.
So I'll talk in a bit more about the miners and how they've
pivoted their businesses into AI.
But you see this across industry sets, including
asset managers and exchanges and software and payments
and banking. There's crypto focused companies that are
broadening their basis into traditional aspects of their industries
and vice versa, where many companies are adopting
crypto as part of their future, a lot like companies are adopting
AI. So there's a hybrid and the addressable market related to our fund has
gotten large. As far as companies that are predominantly Bitcoin
and crypto and blockchain focus where they're predominant businesses
is in those realms. Like that was very small when we started four
plus years ago. You know, that's what makes the market so exciting today is
because those companies have matured.
There's been a lot of syndicate.
There's been a bunch more liquidity that's unlocked in these underlying
companies that's created like an amazing opportunity set for our fund.
I guess the other thing is just the regulatory environment has shifted such that
now the banks, the broker dealers have a little bit more clarity on what they can
do. IPO window seems to be open right now, less of an overhang,
maybe in terms of getting a company public.
Would you say that's a factor as well?
It's been a huge factor. Like there was such a pivot just before the election.
And Trump has obviously been constructive in the industry and his family's
involved privately and in the public markets.
And there's been some important legislation that's helped create the clarity
that the industry was looking for to make capital investments in the industry.
That all has precipitated like a ton of syndicate that we could talk about.
And a lot of companies lining up to join the fray.
The legislative handcuffs have been unlocked and it's clear that there'll be
tons of additional opportunity as legislation improves.
One of the biggest things that's happening this year, I would say, at least in the
venture world, there's just everyone talking about these digital asset treasury
companies. And kind of surprising to me to see a lot of venture funds investing in
some of these things. But what's your take on what we're seeing with these DATs?
And curious if this is sustainable in your eyes.
I've done my best, Matt, to try to understand this business.
And it resembles a lot of situations before because there's been a ton of value
creation and you have to wonder why the predominant number of these companies
don't have any other business other than issuing shares or leveraging up in
creative ways and buying Bitcoin and other crypto currencies.
And they've used a very inflated market valuation to do so, which has been
amazing. But I'm skeptical because that really works in a sensible mind
in a healthy crypto environment, as far as like pricing.
And at such time, we're going to get the next correction in Bitcoin and
Solana and Ethereum.
I'm worried that these NAVs are going to collapse and in many cases trade below
NAV. You're already seeing some of that because there's been such a flurry.
I think Michael Saylor at a conference last week talked about the number of these
companies just in Bitcoin to go from 64 at the beginning of the year to 190 by
last week. 190 public companies just doing Bitcoin treasury, which own a million
Bitcoin or about 5% of everything outstanding on their balance sheets.
So you're seeing a big disparity right now relating to the valuations.
Some of them really haven't got out of the box and are trading at discounts.
Others still trade at three, five, even 20 times and have very inefficient.
It's a great time for us to look at arbitrage opportunities.
You could buy ETFs or broken treasuries against the inflated ones.
But over time, I'm just concerned that I think it's about 20 billion dollars that
have been put into the space is all but a handful are likely to trade at a discount.
Ultimately, is my concern.
Yeah. I mean, if you just look at this academically, I think you'd be saying this
looks like it's something that could attract activist investors.
I really doubt the convert market can handle this scale of capital from some of
these issuers. I'm not sure why the seventh largest coin on coin market cap needs
its fourth debt. It just seems like we've saturated the market a little bit in the
category. Yeah, for sure.
As I mentioned, some of the discounts have collapsed and others have.
I've seen two deals pulled in the last week that were on peripheral currencies.
I think there's only so much capacity that could go into the space.
I would just say that like this whole thing, because it's blown up this year,
there just isn't a lot of commitment on the buy side that I could tell because it
takes an inordinate amount of work to track each company, what's on their balance
sheet, the shares issued, the capital structure, when the unlocks may be
happening. They're using ATMs, so you don't really know how many shares are
outstanding. And then you have to consider borrow rates.
I was looking at borrow rates and some of these earlier this week, and the ones
with unlocks range from like 100 percent to 500 percent if you get a borrow at
all. So those are just nuances on the trades.
And then longer term, you got to think about the fees and the management teams
and what else they may be doing that's differentiated.
But it's very complicated and it's like the Wild West.
I don't think anybody can be dialed on everything that's going on because it's
so fluid.
I want to shift gears a little bit and talk about the Bitcoin mining space.
This is historically not a space that we've really ever invested in just because
of the capital intensity of the business.
But obviously, a lot of these things have gone public over the past decade.
So curious just your views on where that industry was when you started the fund
and then where it is today.
You mentioned this was four years ago.
It's like yesterday when I was trying to understand these businesses.
And even then, I mean, it wasn't that forthright, but from the outset, these are
flawed, most challenged industry to compete in than I've ever come across.
Building a Bitcoin mine is hugely capital intensive, and it leads to a lot of
dilution to build at the outset.
And ultimately, when you know how Bitcoin rewards are allocated, you know, these
miners are spending a lot of money to chase fixed rewards with increasing
difficulty rates, which means the cost of each Bitcoin is more difficult and more
challenging and more costly.
So when I look at the group and I pulled it up recently, there was no EBITDA
growth from the time we launched our fund four and a half years ago through 2024.
And that's in the face of how well Bitcoin has done.
So they held themselves out as Bitcoin surrogates, but have massively under
performed Bitcoin if you just invest in them directly.
When you think about it prospectively, it's even worse.
There's only five percent of the Bitcoin yet to be mined and difficulty
rates continue to go up.
China, Russia and Iran are goosing their output.
And this is all in the face who would want to invest in more infrastructure here
when you've got having in 2028, which is going to virtually wipe out the EBITDA
of almost all the public companies in the United States.
So in my view, challenged industry and they persevered because Bitcoin has been
so strong, but their outlook for Bitcoin profitability beyond 28 is eligible.
Kind of crazy to think about competing against nation states that are not
economics driven.
Some of these countries, you probably have someone in a government that has
access to free power and is standing up a mining operation outside the purview
of their government.
And so it's kind of scary to compete against someone like that.
Without question.
And I always shook my head on why this would be a good business.
And we had to focus on it because when we launched, this was probably 50 percent
of the market value in the crypto blockchain ecosystem.
And today it's still important, but it's been productive because we're long
and short and there's been a lot of alpha opportunities.
Maybe that's a good dovetailing to kind of what this looks like today.
AI, HPC, I don't know if we talked about that on the podcast four years ago.
I mean, the world looks a lot different today.
We have chat GPT now.
We have a lot of capital going into the AI space, but it seems to me as someone
that doesn't follow this every single day that a lot of these businesses have
pivoted into the AI space.
Curious just what it looks like in the future here.
Better to be lucky than to be smart.
And I don't know if any of them would share this directly, but I think they
basically won a lifeline or lottery ticket like this was not contrived.
And one thing that Bitcoin miners had to do well to compete was to access power
and have power contracts.
Some of them had the foresight to lock up significant power and attractive prices,
but never did they ever think that they were going to use this for anything but
Bitcoin. What's going on in the last, it's only a little over a year ago when the
first deal was announced, but surging demand that we all hear about from the
hyperscalers and what are called Neo clouds, which are surrogates that are
running these huge data centers and leasing out their GPUs.
This demand is really insatiable in their term.
Anyone anywhere that has access to power and good land and water and with a good
location for latency is very valuable because there's only so much of that
available to be energized over the next year or so where you can actually build a
data center over the next two years, say by 2027 and be up and running.
And there's only a few such sites and some of these Bitcoin miners having to
be sitting on them.
And the first announcement was with Coreweave and CoreScientific a little over a
year ago. Since that time, you know, there's been at least eight other
significant deals.
And at this point, if you look at the top 10 Bitcoin miners, the public ones,
they've all pivoted to say that this direction is their future going forward or
part of the future.
I visited with citizens, cell site analysts last week that focus on data
centers, and I reflected on a report they wrote where there's 54 gigawatts of power
shortfall due to the data center demand between now and 2030.
I think that's enough to power about 25 million homes.
So, again, to suggest these miners were in the right place at the right time is an
understatement. The models are much different.
It's hugely capital intensive and complex.
But when you sign one of these agreements, you get a steady predictable cash flow,
which is a lot different and better than the uncertainty about Bitcoin
volatility.
Do you think that means that Bitcoin mining in the U.S.
just kind of tails off to zero and it's just uneconomic miners here?
What do you think this means, I guess, more from the perspective of the Bitcoin
network and where this is mined?
I've given that some thought and most of the companies I'm speaking with have
either reached their run rate for their production on their exit hash or their
targeting growth, you know, maybe for the next year and then they're going to peak
out. But that will be their persistent run rate until 2028.
And when you do the math on the halving as we have, yeah, I think most of the
capacity in the U.S.
will be uneconomic and be mothballed.
Either it'll be run complimentary as a secondary business to these companies,
HPC initiatives, or will just be curtailed.
So I do think the way things look, that the direction for Bitcoin mining in the
U.S., at least for these public providers, will be meaningfully lower as we look
forward into 2028 and beyond.
Yeah, I guess there's other factors there around what if a fee market emerges on
top of the block reward?
Obviously, the price of Bitcoin factors into this.
But from where we sit today, I'd say I agree with you.
It's hard to imagine that if you have the opportunity to power in the HPC
category, why would you be mining Bitcoin?
Without question. And if you haven't asked what I'm thinking about, though, is
it's a really curious time for these companies because they've never built an
HPC AI data center and they're very complex.
And this is a new initiative.
So while it is kind of opaque what their future is in Bitcoin mining, there are a
lot of uncertainties and execution around building a different business that these
companies have not been in.
That actually kind of dovetails into where I want to go next, which is just how
do you differentiate these companies that started as Bitcoin miners?
Like, what does it take to win in the category?
In the past, I've thought that those that are ready earlier are the de facto
winners. But at the end of the day, it's really just how much power you have, how
quality it is and how soon it can be energized and how close you may be to a grid
or an urban area.
When I think about investing in the space, some of the participants or players have
already contracted most of their megawatts.
Those have been repriced higher because of the visibility of the cash flow.
With that said, there's not a lot of upside to their business models over the next few
years, given those stocks have been revalued to kind of the way we look at the present
value of the payments once those data centers are up and running.
So when we try to distinguish and we wonder or try to discern who has those best
assets, who's most likely next in the queue to sign meaningful contracts.
And I'm trying to simplify that much and it has really almost nothing to do with
their Bitcoin businesses, believe it or not.
Yeah, it just sounds like just this insatiable demand for power and energy.
You seeing any indication that nuclear will be a solution here that either factors
into the AI HPC market or to the Bitcoin market for that matter?
It's really interesting how our digital infrastructure strategy has evolved or
dovetailed, but these grids have tremendous demands.
And I mentioned, you know, the shortfall.
And so these utilities are being very mindful about signing new contracts.
And even when you sign a contract, these AI HPC and cloud computing centers, they
can't go down like a Bitcoin mining.
It just really messes up all the economics.
So if there's any power issues they have to protect against, so there's generators
and redundancy at every one of these facilities.
But I've spent some time looking at alternative power and, you know, it's not
only nuclear, like you can look at some of these public companies and they've been
revalued, even though nuclear won't even be an opportunity, but they're taking
orders for like 2030 and beyond.
But you also have to think about natural gas and pipelines.
I have a call this afternoon with one of the big MLPs to discuss with them.
About building pipelines toward AI HPC data centers of natural gas to provide
the power, either redundant or otherwise.
So it's really fascinating.
And in my mind, it even brings like wind and solar back into play.
So all these things are fun to think about and you want to think about them
proactively from an investment standpoint, because that's where the puck is going.
I guess that's a really interesting point to around the, just the ability to
sustain going down and coming back up.
Because for Bitcoin mining, that is fine, right?
You could shut off the miners, turn them back on.
Wouldn't be the end of the world.
Obviously not ideal, but for these AI HPC use cases, that just seems
like that would be a disaster.
Yeah, I mean, that is my understanding.
You just can't turn off these computations and turn them back on.
You likely have to fix whatever it is and go back to last month or something.
So I don't even know that's beyond my technological prowess, but that's just
one of a number of uncertainties and execution risks as we move forward here.
When you think about just the risk factors and how do you analyze one
business versus another, or how do you underwrite the risk of getting long
a certain name or getting short a certain name?
What are the things that you think about?
It's important to have the team.
Some of these have had more foresight, these miners, and they brought on
proven experts in the industry and power and in data center, presumably
their prowess to execute is going to be better than some others that are
just now pivoting, but you got to build out and learn a whole new business.
So I think about the management team, their ability to finance
because it's very expensive.
This CapEx is exponentially larger than the Bitcoin miners.
And I think about, you know, as I mentioned, power, and I think about
strain on the infrastructure and those kinds of risks, because, you know,
whether it be the grid or water, there's going to be dislocations as demand
continues to rise more than the ability to supply it.
So I think about the answers I get to those type of considerations.
And then I think quite a bit about their customers and counterparty
risks and risks to these deals, because I think about these very much like real
estate investment trusts, actually.
And they may become real estate investment trusts because it's really
just a landlord and a tenant.
And some of these tenants would never be bankable.
If you just looked at their balance sheets, there's these companies called
NeoClouds that have been the predominant lessee of these AI HPC data centers.
And they're just insatiable.
This one large one has spending $23 billion in CapEx this year needs to
borrow $19 billion to fund it.
And they don't really have a balance sheet, but yet they're signing
multi-billion dollar contracts with a lot of these companies.
So I just wonder, you know, what it looks like over time and do they have the
fortitude to make it work and pay even if they want to.
And then when you think about these NeoClouds, they're signing with their
customers for four or five years, but they're signing 15 year contracts with
these HPC data centers.
And, you know, that mismatch creates a lot of concern for me also.
So what happens in five years?
So I think a lot about the counterparty risk.
And one of the deals last month or even a few weeks ago is backstopped by
Oracle, which would give me a lot more confidence than some of these
more up and coming companies.
It's unbelievable.
I mean, Oracle is a name that I don't really follow, but what a story there.
And some of the forecasts coming out of that business seem to have people
pretty excited just from a category perspective.
What a story.
It's really remarkable.
$144 billion of revenues they expect in 2030 from their cloud business.
That's undeniable, even though most of that's with one customer, which is
also undercapitalized at the time.
But that announcement and thinking through that has informed my recent
thinking on the space because there is so much demand that good company, bad
company, good management, whatever your strategy outlook, if you have good
power, it's clearly going to be in demand.
So there's going to be general winners here.
And the ones that don't have access to power, as I discussed,
I think are the losers.
When you think about just the broader ecosystem that you want to play in, in
terms of the types of businesses that will go public here over the next few years,
do you segment the fund between business models?
Obviously looking at an AI data center, Bitcoin mining companies, probably going
to look a lot different from a couple of years from now, you're going to have
compliance software businesses in the crypto space going public.
How do you toggle between the various different categories here?
I think I mentioned this was kind of somewhat at the fault because it has been
and still is a big part of the industry.
And if you define it as a blockchain industry and, you know, over time there's
been $70 billion, I think of companies that have gone public this year that are
not miners that are in crypto and blockchain.
And there's a whole list of other companies that Matt, you and I know that
are on the fringe and likely to come public.
So I think you're going to get that natural diversification into, you know,
as you said, compliance and payments and software, you know, there's more asset
managers coming. So I'm looking for broader diversification.
And I think from our perspective, an increasing portion of the portfolio will
be targeted on a lot of these public companies, some of which are clear winners
and some of which are very suspect.
Do you think the hedge fund industry evolves over time such that you have
connectivity and the ability to trade cryptocurrency through your prime broker
and maybe hedge an equity position by doing something in the liquid
cryptocurrency market?
How do you see just the plumbing of this working from running the business over
the next few years?
Well, this isn't my area of expertise.
I mean, I think like all aspects, I talked to the top of the call, there's a
convergence going on and, you know, we're evaluating our transition to a prime
broker because they're at the forefront of thinking about some of those
possibilities and they have plans.
There's crypto native type prime brokers and there's traditional equity prime
brokers. And I think they either merge or work together.
And, you know, over time, I think you see these combinations being the
mainstay. There's no reason they shouldn't merge.
Yeah, I think that's right.
The last question on my side would just be, what's this been like culturally with
the people that work at Intrinsic Edge and also your clients?
I'd imagine that early days you had some folks that were like, what the hell is
Bitcoin? Why are we spending our time here?
What's it been like to grow this within the firm?
It's so much fun to be in the weeds on this research.
And there's a growing enthusiasm everywhere, I think, as all the listeners
know as well. And there's a lot of enthusiasm within the firm.
There's a growing enthusiasm about the opportunity set, and we're getting a lot
of inbounds from all different type of potential investors.
And I think it's a lot of fun.
I think we're in the early innings.
And, yeah, I'm very excited.
It's a really novel strategy.
And I mean, hey, look, not a lot of people have a four year track record running
public equities in this category.
And maybe you're the only person on that list.
So thanks again for coming on.
Great catching up.
Thank you, Nat.
That was a fun one.
I always enjoy having Mark on the show and hearing about how the public markets
are evolving for blockchain focused companies.
To learn more about Intrinsic Edge, please visit their website,
www.intrinsicedge.com
or email them at info at intrinsicedge.com.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To learn more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc.
And to listen to all of our podcast episodes, please visit
castleisland.vc slash podcast or just click on the tab on our website.
Thanks for listening.